<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Green World - OpenNote</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="feeds/opennote.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2025-06-15T20:35:00+08:00</updated><entry><title>Beyond the Letters: Discussion of the Dynamics between ESG Rating Providers and Sustainability Disclosure Requirements in Mainland China ｜ 关于中国大陆本土ESG评级机构与可持续发展披露要求的一些思考</title><link href="china-esg-ratings-zh.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-06-15T20:35:00+08:00</published><updated>2025-06-15T20:35:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Iris</name></author><id>tag:None,2025-06-15:china-esg-ratings-zh.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Some thoughts about ESG Rating Providers and Sustainability Disclosure Requirements in Mainland China. | 关于中国大陆本土ESG评级机构与可持续发展披露要求的一些思考&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://1drv.ms/b/c/da576873c7b9d13d/EWDU835yHVlLj3lvOw4Fj8sBkwGnYmM2T1AkP2n2vvy2yw?e=7jP7Gs"&gt;Link to the paper/ 论文链接&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.kaggle.com/code/qimengshi/a-share-esg-analysis-codes-20250615"&gt;Link to dataset and codes/ 数据集和代码链接&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Abstract | 概要&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ESG ratings play a foundational role in supplying data for designing ESG investing strategies, yet significant rating divergence and retrospective rating updates can undermine the usability of ESG rating data. This study examines how the evolving sustainability disclosure standards in Mainland China influence ESG rating convergence among four domestic providers (Wind, SynTao Green Finance, Sino-Securities Index, and SusallWave). While the gradual establishment of a sustainability disclosure system reduce overall divergence, sector-level disagreements remain, which are particularly salient in Utilities, Materials, and Consumer Discretionary sectors. At individual company level, high emitting product producers and conglomerates face unique challenges in evaluating and disclosing their ESG performance. The findings suggest ESG rating providers can contribute to the development of robust disclosure and evaluation frameworks by offering sector specific insights.    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;ESG评级数据是ESG投资的基石，为投资策略的设计提供了必要的基础数据，但不同评级机构间显著的评级分歧与回溯性的评级变动可能削弱ESG评级数据的可用性。本研究探讨了中国大陆不断完善的可持续发展披露标准如何影响四家本土评级机构（万得，商道融绿，华证指数以及盟浪）的ESG评级一致性。尽管可持续发展披露体系的逐步建立降低了整体分歧，但行业层面的分歧仍然存在，在公用事业、原材料和非必需消费品行业尤为突出。就个体企业而言，高碳排产品生产商和综合性集团企业在评估与披露ESG绩效时面临独特挑战。研究建议ESG评级机构可以通过提供有关不同行业的ESG洞察，助力构建更完善的披露与评估体系。 &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Key findings | 主要发现&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regarding the four Chinese ESG rating providers analyzed in this paper:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;关于本文分析的四家本土ESG评级机构：&lt;/strong&gt;     &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The four providers share similar data sources, data collection processes and technology. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;四家机构采用相似的数据来源、收集流程及技术。 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The four providers differentiate their ratings from each other through methodologies. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;四家机构通过不同的方法论实现评级差异化。 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Transparency around data, methodologies and procedures remains to be improved. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;数据、方法论及流程的透明度仍有待提升。 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Despite the providers’ intention to cover historical ratings, backtracked data may be subject to look ahead bias. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;虽然四家机构都覆盖历史评级，但回溯数据可能存在前瞻性偏差。 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The four providers are still at an early stage in adopting international best practices. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;四家机构在国际最佳实践应用方面仍处于初级阶段。    &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regarding the ESG rating distribution of China A Shares:&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;A股ESG评级分布特征：&lt;/strong&gt;     &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The China A share ESG ratings given by the four providers are generally skewed toward higher notches. In other words, those providers tend to avoid giving the worst ratings. There are also a disproportionate number of companies being considered as “average.” &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;四家机构对A股的ESG评级分布向较高等级倾斜，鲜少给出最低评级，很多企业集中在“中等”评级水平。      &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Regarding the ESG rating divergence:&lt;/strong&gt;   &lt;br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;ESG评级分歧：&lt;/strong&gt;    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The pairwise correlations between the 2024 Q4 ESG ratings given by the four providers turn out to be surprisingly high, ranging from 0.55 to 0.71 with an average of 0.61, all statistically significant. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2024年四季度四家机构ESG评级的组间相关性较高（0.55-0.71，均值0.61），且均显著。 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since 2020, the average correlation of three ESG rating providers has significantly increased from 0.40 to 0.64. One driving force of such convergence is the increasing quantity and standardization of companies’ sustainability disclosures as an internationally aligned sustainability disclosure system is being developed in Mainland China.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;2020年以来，三家评级机构的平均相关性从0.40显著提升至0.64，主要驱动力是中国大陆与国际接轨的可持续发展披露体系推动了更多企业披露更标准化的可持续发展信息。 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At the sector level, ESG rating divergence varies from 0.7 to 1.39 notches with &lt;strong&gt;Utilities, Materials, and Consumer Discretionary&lt;/strong&gt; being the top 3 sectors with the highest level of disagreement between ESG rating providers. Sector level rating distributions can vary a lot from normal-like to bi-modal and staircase distributions. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;行业层面，ESG评级分歧度介于0.7-1.39个等级之间，其中&lt;strong&gt;公用事业、原材料和非必需消费品&lt;/strong&gt;是评级机构分歧最大的三个行业。行业间的评级分布形态差异显著—从类似正态分布到双峰分布乃至阶梯式分布均有呈现。 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At individual company level, &lt;strong&gt;high emitting product producers and conglomerates&lt;/strong&gt;, with their own challenges in evaluating and disclosing ESG performance, are more likely to trigger disagreement between rating providers. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;企业层面，&lt;strong&gt;高碳排产品生产商和综合性集团企业&lt;/strong&gt;面临ESG绩效评估与披露的特殊挑战，更易引发评级机构间的意见分歧。 &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="OpenNote"></category><category term="OpenNote"></category></entry><entry><title>CEva &amp; IAR</title><link href="projects-zh.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2025-01-06T11:20:00+08:00</published><updated>2025-01-06T11:20:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Iris</name></author><id>tag:None,2025-01-06:projects-zh.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;职业评估开源软件（CEva）和年度报告（IAR）&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;希娃（CEva）&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;希娃（CEva）是一个专门用于职业评估（&lt;strong&gt;C&lt;/strong&gt;areer &lt;strong&gt;EVa&lt;/strong&gt;luation）的开源软件。  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;CEva is an open-source app built specifically for &lt;strong&gt;C&lt;/strong&gt;areer &lt;strong&gt;EVa&lt;/strong&gt;luation. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;网页版app&lt;a href="https://ceva-career-evaluation.streamlit.app"&gt;链接&lt;/a&gt;：https://ceva-career-evaluation.streamlit.app&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;年度报告 (IAR)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;2024年度报告：“温水煮懒獴”&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IAR 2024: Boiling Year in Laziness
&lt;a href="https://www.canva.com/design/DAGafbupEMQ/pd7_8-6t7sQxoS6X7ucm7Q/view?utm_content=DAGafbupEMQ&amp;amp;utm_campaign=designshare&amp;amp;utm_medium=link2&amp;amp;utm_source=uniquelinks&amp;amp;utlId=h118692f26a"&gt;公开版链接&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;2023年度报告：从“绿色世界”到“红色世界”-2023年的双赤字&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;IAR 2023: FROM GREEN WORLD TO RED WORLD The Double Negative of 2023
&lt;a href="https://www.canva.com/design/DAF7C5Fozzk/ZzK6_5BVimC0TcALCD3fqg/edit?utm_content=DAF7C5Fozzk&amp;amp;utm_campaign=designshare&amp;amp;utm_medium=link2&amp;amp;utm_source=sharebutton"&gt;公开版链接&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="OpenNote"></category><category term="OpenNote"></category></entry><entry><title>Field Study | 考察手记</title><link href="field-study-zh.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2024-11-03T11:20:00+08:00</published><updated>2024-11-03T11:20:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Iris</name></author><id>tag:None,2024-11-03:field-study-zh.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;世界那么大，我想用脚步去丈量，用眼睛去观察，用嘴巴去品味，用笔尖去记录。&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h2&gt;考察手记链接汇总&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;中国篇&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://1drv.ms/b/c/da576873c7b9d13d/ES5m-Ev4sgVBsyvtkl2JRfUB1O-zY31i5C6AstudnphmOA?e=7jxs6X"&gt;考察手记1：珠海斗门镇&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="OpenNote"></category><category term="OpenNote"></category></entry></feed>