<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Green World - Snippets</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="feeds/snippets.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2023-03-22T15:12:00+08:00</updated><entry><title>杂碎 (Snippets)</title><link href="snippets-zh.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-03-22T15:12:00+08:00</published><updated>2023-03-22T15:12:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Iris</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-03-22:snippets-zh.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A tree hole to dump thoughts｜思绪杂碎&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;一年前的杂碎板块（Snippets）是用来记录日常情绪化的瞬间的。
一年后，我不再那么emo了，我想拿这个板块来记录思绪（threads of thoughts）。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the threads of thoughts, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to weave a coherent net, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;to wrap innovation and dream.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在 GPT 被狂欢的时代，&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我像个顽固的守旧派，&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;相信积累 domain knowledge 不可或缺，&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;主动 judge 信息，&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;而不是被动接受 AIGC。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;What It Takes by Stephen A. Schwarzman&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Teaching, I came to believe, is about more than sharing knowledge. You have to remove the obstacles in people's way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Others&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I only hope that we never lose sight of one thing - that it was all started by a mouse. - Walt Disney&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speak less than you know; have more than you show. 怀璧慎显，博识谨言。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I was young and free and my imagination had no limits, I dreamed of changing the world. As I grew older and wiser, I discovered the world would not change, so I shortened my sights somewhat and decided to change only my country. But it, too, seemed immovable. As I grew into my twilight years, in one last desperate attempt, I settled for changing only my family, those close to me, but alas, they would have none of it. And now, as I lie on my deathbed, I suddenly realize: If I had only changed myself first, then by example, I would have changed my family. From their inspiration and encouragement, I would then have been able to better my country and who knows, I may have even changed the world. - Westminster Abbey&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Snippets"></category><category term="Snippets"></category></entry></feed>