<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Green World - Snippets</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="feeds/snippets.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2023-05-29T21:00:00+08:00</updated><entry><title>杂碎 (Snippets)</title><link href="snippets-zh.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-05-29T21:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2023-05-29T21:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Iris</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-05-29:snippets-zh.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A tree hole to dump thoughts｜思绪杂碎&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;一年前的杂碎板块（Snippets）是用来记录日常情绪化的瞬间的。
一年后，我不再那么emo了，我想拿这个板块来记录思绪（threads of thoughts）。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the threads of thoughts, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to weave a coherent net, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;to wrap innovation and dream.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在 GPT 被狂欢的时代，&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我像个顽固的守旧派，&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;相信积累 domain knowledge 不可或缺，&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;主动 judge 信息，&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;而不是被动接受 AIGC。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;《大量废弃社会》&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;所以说真正决定“新闻价值”的，是特定时代、国家及人民看待问题的态度，对此做出筛选的人则是编辑和记者。(pp. 4)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“新闻”一词的字面意义就是“新的见闻”。最新发生的事、不常出现的事、发生变化的事容易写成报道，然而那些即使存在问题，却为社会所默许，变化缓慢，难以进入到大众视线当中的事，却总是难以成文。记者的“基本使命”-监督权力并与之斗争。(pp. 5)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;我认为发达国家的民众对媒体越来越不信任的原因不仅在于贫富差距扩大化与网络舆论极端化，还有对“与自身息息相关的问题”被媒体边缘化而感到的不满。(pp. 6)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“商品陈旧化”理论始终是商业模式的核心 (pp. 10)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;在团队分工合作的情况下，工人会经手不同种类服装的整个制作过程，因此在几年后，工人的技术水平会得到提高，工资也会上涨。但在孟加拉国那样的国家里，制作工序和流程被细分化，即使刚刚进厂的工人也能迅速投入工作。甚至有的人进了工厂，整整一年都在安装服装右侧的纽扣。这样的工作无论干上多久，工人的技术水平也不会提升，工资也不会上涨。至于企业方面，由于成本降低，也做好了商品滞销的心理准备，只要整体能盈利就行。(pp. 17)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;才能变现 (pp. 19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“消费者的成熟””不囿于个人欲望，与社会及自然环境共生意识的觉醒“ (pp. 23)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“惜物”精神 (pp. 59)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;服装行业解决方案：（1）公开价格。案例：10YC，GUSTIN，Everlane，Factelier，People Tree（2）有效利用技术。案例：KASHIYAMA the Smart Tailor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;食品行业井出女士的观点：（1）每人每天都浪费了一碗米饭（2）错失销售机会（3）“便利店记账法”与“销售有效期”（4）奇特的“三分之一”法则（5）将“减少垃圾产生”放在首位（6）借助消费者的力量改变食品行业。案例：多利安面包店、Gragger、食品银行与食品募捐、“凉/烤豆腐指数”、需求预测指数、荻野餐厅、“3010”运动、“狗狗袋”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;如果公司遵循“销量全靠降价”这一方针，顾客会越来越难以感受到商品的真正价值，服装的生产者们也会受到伤害，这对他们双方都是一种辜负。(pp. 70)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“让生产者与顾客双方都满意”的宗旨；精心生产的服装能够改变人们的日常生活；注重保持游戏心态和愉快的心情 (pp. 72)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;它既涉及劳动问题与整个服务业的症结，更是一种诞生于新型商业活动之中的“人为创造的习俗” (pp. 96)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"三方得利"，近江商人，卖家、买家、社会。并不鼓励一味扩张，而是“恰到好处”，并将有益的事物与他人分享。(pp. 97)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“在琳琅满目的商品中挑选”已经成为了顾客所习以为常的行为 (pp. 97)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;所谓的经典，就是抓住事物本质，在任何时代都不会过时的东西，因此无需进行改变。(pp. 119)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;第一代人：从欧洲引进面包和葡萄酒并尝试制作；第二代人：在日本用欧洲的材料制作出正宗地道的产品；第三代人：用日本的原料，结合日本的气候与水土，制作出符合日本人口味的产品 （pp. 120)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;资源共享型社会 (pp. 153)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;道德时尚 (pp. 156)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;始终在价格、流行度或便利性这些可变换的价值上进行竞争，只会让人疲惫不堪。(pp. 167)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;自然而然地与生产者共情 （pp. 174)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Lean In by Sheryl Sandberg《向前一步》&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even worse, the messages sent to girls can move beyond encouraging superficial traits and veer into explicitly discouraging leadership. (pp. 21)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The gender stereotypes introduced in childhood are reinforced throughout our lives and become self-fulfilling prophecies. (pp. 23)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Women are not thinking about 'having it all,' they are worried about losing it all - their jobs, their children's health, their families' financial stability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Framing the issue as work-life balance - as if the two were diametrically opposed - practically ensures work will lose out. (pp. 25)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fear is the root of so many of the barriers that women face. Fear of not being liked. Fear of making the wrong choice. Fear of drawing negative attention. Fear of overreaching. Fear of being judged. Fear of failure. And the holy trinity of fear: the fear of being a bad mother/wife/daughter. (pp. 26)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;undistort the distortion (pp. 35)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fake it till you feel it (pp. 36)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opportunities are not well defined but, instead, come from someone jumping in to do something. That something then become his job.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is hard to visualize someone as a leader if she is always waiting to be told what to do. (pp. 37)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is no perfect fit when you're looking for the next big thing to do. You have to take opportunities and make an opportunity fit for you. (pp. 38)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For women, "self-doubt becomes a form of self-defense." We put ourselves done before others. (pp. 44)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Owning one's success is key to achieving more success. (pp. 47)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"gender discount" problem (pp. 48)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The goal of a successful negotiation is to achieve our objectives and continue to have people like us. (pp. 50)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pronouns matter, justify their requests, relentlessly pleasant (pp. 51)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you want to change things, you can't please everyone. If you do please everyone, you aren't making enough progress. (pp. 55)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a long-term dream and an eighteen month plan (pp. 58)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Employees who concentrate on results and impact are the most valuable. Set more personal goals for learning new skills in the next eighteen months. (pp. 63)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Letting the other side make the first offer is often crucial to achieving favorable terms. (pp. 64)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In business, being risk averse can result in stagnation. Seeking out diverse experience is useful preparation for leadership. (pp. 66)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The most common way people give up their power is by thinking they don't have any. (pp. 68)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The men were focusing on how to manage a business and the women focusing on how to manage a career. (pp. 71)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Excel and you will get a mentor. (pp. 73)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Asking for input is not a sign of weakness but often the first step to finding a path forward. (pp. 76)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All advice is autobiographical. (pp. 80)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As we learn to speak appropriately, we lose something in authenticity. (pp. 82)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;not brutally honest but delicately honest (pp. 83)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Great leadership is "conscious" leadership - Fred Kofman&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When communicating hard truths, less is often more, (pp. 85)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feedback, like truth, is not absolute. Feedback is an opinion, grounded in observations and experiences, which allows us to know what impression we make on others. (pp. 88)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being open to hearing the truth means taking responsibility for mistakes. (pp. 89-90)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Motivation comes from working on things we care about. It also comes from working with people we care about. (pp. 94)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;True leadership stems from individuality that is honestly and sometimes imperfectly expressed. Strive for authenticity over perfection. (pp. 97)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But when it comes to integrating career and family, planning too far in advance can close doors rather than open them. (pp. 99)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Women wind up leaving the workforce precisely because of things they did to stay in the workforce. (pp. 100)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anyone lucky enough to have options should keep them open. (pp. 110)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's not about biology, but about consciousness. (pp. 115)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trying to do it all and expecting that it all can be done exactly right is a recipe for disappointment. (pp. 131)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be a perfectionist in only the things that mattered. (pp. 131)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Done is better than perfect. (pp. 133)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setting obtainable goals is key to happiness. Instead of perfection, we should aim for sustainable and fulfilling. Success is making the best choices we can... and accepting them. The secret is there is no secret-just doing the best you can with what you've got. (pp. 148)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whoever has power takes over the noun-and the norm-while the less powerful get an adjective. (pp. 149)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No one wants her achievements modified. (pp. 149)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leadership is about making others better as a result of your presence and making sure that impact lasts in your absence. Social gains are never handed out. They must be seized. (pp. 167)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Equal opportunity is not equal unless everyone receives the encouragement that makes seizing those opportunities possible. (pp. 170)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To feel comfortable with our choices and to feel validated by those around us. (pp. 178)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our job is not to make young women grateful. It is to make them ungrateful so they keep going. (pp. 182)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Haroun and the Sea of Stories《哈乐与故事海》&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A blind man's blindness must feel twice as wretched then. - Rashid (pp. 22)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Need's a slippery snake. Need's a funny fish: It makes people untruthful. - Butt (pp. 24)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No story comes from nowhere; new stories are born from old. - Iff (pp. 74)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You know how people are, new things, always new. The old tales, nobody cares. - Iff (pp. 74)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dark, my sirs, has its fascinations: mystery, strangeness, romance ... - Iff (pp. 91)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't you know girls have to fool people everyday of their lives if they want to get anywhere? - Blabbermouth (pp. 95)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You keep a lot of different tales in the air, and juggle them up and down, and if you're good you don't drop any. So maybe juggling is a kind of storytelling, too. - Haroun (pp. 97)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That's the trouble with you sad city types: you think a place has to be miserable and dull as ditchwater before you believe it's real. - Blabbermouth (pp. 103)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And is not the Power of Speech the greatest Power of all? Then surely it must be exercised to the full. - Butt the Hoopoe (pp. 107)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is all for Love, which is a wonderful and dashing matter. But which can also be a very foolish thing. - Mali (pp. 108)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Silence had its own grace and beauty (just as speech could be graceless and ugly); and that Action could be as noble as words; and that creatures of darkness could be as lovely as the children of the light. - Haroun (pp. 113)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So peace with the Chupwalas means Peace with their Shadows, too. - Mudra (pp. 121)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is a sad time when a Chupwala cannot even trust his own shadow. - Mudra (pp. 122)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We lost touch with our beginnings, with our roots, our wellspring, our source. - Iff (pp. 134)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The worst things of all can look so normal and, well, dull. - Haroun (pp. 141)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;War makes people crude. (pp. 174)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They had talked through everything so fully, fought hard, remained united, supported each other when required to do so, and in general looked like a force with a common purpose. All those arguments and debates, all that openness, had created powerful bonds of fellowship between them. / Their vows of silence and their habits of secrecy had made them suspicious and distrustful of one another. (pp. 175)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Happy endings are much rarer in stories, and also in life, than most people think. You could almost say they are the exceptions, not the rule. - Walrus (pp. 191)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Happy endings must come at the end of something. If they happen in the middle of a story, or an adventure, or the like, all they do is cheer things up for a while. - Walrus (pp. 192)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Money isn't everything; no money is nothing at all. - Rashid &amp;amp; Mail Coach (pp. 197)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;What It Takes by Stephen A. Schwarzman《苏世民：我的经验与教训》&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Teaching, I came to believe, is about more than sharing knowledge. You have to remove the obstacles in people's way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;其他/Others&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I only hope that we never lose sight of one thing - that it was all started by a mouse. - Walt Disney&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speak less than you know; have more than you show. 怀璧慎显，博识谨言。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I was young and free and my imagination had no limits, I dreamed of changing the world. As I grew older and wiser, I discovered the world would not change, so I shortened my sights somewhat and decided to change only my country. But it, too, seemed immovable. As I grew into my twilight years, in one last desperate attempt, I settled for changing only my family, those close to me, but alas, they would have none of it. And now, as I lie on my deathbed, I suddenly realize: If I had only changed myself first, then by example, I would have changed my family. From their inspiration and encouragement, I would then have been able to better my country and who knows, I may have even changed the world. - Westminster Abbey&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;我们最后变成什么样，并不取决于我们选择了哪条道路，而是取决于我们的内心。- 欧·亨利&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;莫言见到马尔克斯后要说的第一句话：“先生，我在梦中与你一起喝过咖啡，但哥伦比亚的咖啡里是有中国绿茶的味道。”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;周国平：爱是关切，关切就会在乎，在乎就难免挑剔，于是生出无穷的恩怨。（保护爱心，拒绝冷漠）&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;泰戈尔：把自己活成一道光，因为你不知道谁会借着你的光，走出黑暗。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;给品类取名的要点：有根、好感、直白&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;或许，成年人的孤独，就是悲喜自渡，而这也正是我们难得的自由。-马尔克斯《百年孤独》&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;白日不到处，青春恰自来。苔花如米小，也学牡丹开。-清·袁枚&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5个谈话技巧：（1）先用认同提醒对方“咱们是一伙的” （2）表达赞赏，调动情感力量（3）帮对方看到事情的另一面（4）重申双方共同的价值观（5）提出具体行动方案，以此建立起共同成长的伙伴关系。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;领导力是你能不能，敢不敢让人、让事情产生积极的改变。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;真正的领导力是做自己。-万维钢《真正的领导力是做自己》&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;斯隆认为：专业人才不应该透露自己的兴趣、信念和私人生活，这是他的私事，和专业无关，所以他都隐去了。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;作为一个社会人，如果你在领导位置上，不管是在企业还是在政府，你得把自己的爱好隐藏起来。因为，你的爱好就是别人进攻你的缺口。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;喜怒哀乐之未发，谓之中；发而皆中节，谓之和。中也者，天下之大本也；和也者，天下之达道也。致中和，天地位焉，万物育焉。-《中庸》&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;什么是素直之心？简单说，就是没有束缚的心，即不被情感、经验、偏见、利害关系等束缚，客观而真实地看待事物的心。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;年轻人，希望你们在追逐梦想的路上，能够抽出一点时间来静思冥想，排除无谓的干扰，保持纯正的内心。希望你们不被五光十色的世界迷惑，不被物欲和金钱左右，能够始终不忘初心，一心一意。-松下幸之助&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;不完美，不是孩子的缺点，而是人的特点。-新教育研究院院长李镇西&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;喜欢的东西还是喜欢，只是不再强求；害怕的东西还是害怕，只是敢于面对。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“八胜七败”维持相对的平衡，是世间万事得以永续的秘诀。-松浦弥太郎&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;人活得累，不是人太聪明，而是人太愚蠢。绝大多数的人为活而活，而不是为生命而活。这是人的悲哀。多数的人，把自己的一生活成一个夺取的过程，而不是认识和体验生命的过程。-傅菲&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;每个人的高度和宽度，就是活着的境界。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;真正的庄重是有温度的，这种温度就是人情味。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;朋友，始终是那些久处不厌的人。-马德&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;人生不受环境的支配，只受自己习惯思想的恐吓。-赫胥黎&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“狐媚”面前，宜自律，须自持；“贪泉”面前，自强者改造环境，清廉者不惧环境，弱者则被环境所吞噬。-齐世明&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;语言的尽头是音乐的开始。-海涅&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;不要拒绝意外，因为意外是你与世界互相试探的机会。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;图图：非洲人有一种叫作ubuntu的东西，他们相信每个人都是因别人的存在而存在的。“我”与大家紧紧相连。在他们看来，“孤独的人”是不存在的，因为你为群体的共同利益而工作，所以你存在于群体中。当你有了归属，也就有了你自己。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;亚里士多德：羡慕是别人的好运给自己造成的痛苦。在当下，有些人衡量人生价值的标准，不是自己本身的内在价值，而是环境与他人等参照物-别人得到的你没得到，却不去想一想你得到的别人也未必拥有。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;法国社会学家布尔迪厄《继承人》：出身不利的孩子详细学习着帕特农神庙的平面图，却未曾离开自己居住的省份。对一些人来说，学到精英文化是用很大的代价换来的成功；对另一些人来说，这只是一种继承。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;成长是为了让自己的精神世界能够容纳更多相反的道理，并且知道在什么时候使用什么道理。-罗振宇&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Snippets"></category><category term="Snippets"></category></entry><entry><title>写在读书日</title><link href="on-world-book-day-zh.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-04-23T21:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2023-04-23T21:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Iris</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-04-23:on-world-book-day-zh.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;书是生活的影子，是一面镜子。&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;书是生活的影子，是一面镜子。&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;书总在意想不到的时候出现.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;em&gt;Books are shadows of life, casting shadows in my heart.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div align = "left"&gt;
   &lt;div&gt;**********&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;还在城大的一个雨夜，为了听龙应台的讲座，买了一本&lt;strong&gt;《天长地久》&lt;/strong&gt;，从此，和家人在一起就是我最期待的天长地久。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;曾经带着&lt;strong&gt;《What it takes》&lt;/strong&gt;（《苏世民：我的经验与教训》）去建行面试，读完第二章，我知道自己缺了什么。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;在最迷茫的时候，遇到了南怀瑾老师的&lt;strong&gt;《禅与生命的认知初讲》&lt;/strong&gt;，痛苦的时候，就念老师说的“去你妈的”，滚吧！&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;几个月前看完了拖了几年的&lt;strong&gt;《灰犀牛》&lt;/strong&gt;，前几天突然在爸爸的书架上找到了&lt;strong&gt;《黑天鹅》&lt;/strong&gt;，书页已经泛黄，老爸看没看完我不知道，但是我今年一定会看。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;最近“现代化”是人民日报上的高频词，前两天爸爸带回来一本&lt;strong&gt;《中国式现代化论纲》&lt;/strong&gt;，我多少要研读一下。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;给弟弟买生日礼物，为了凑包邮，我选择了&lt;strong&gt;《Lean In》&lt;/strong&gt;（《向前一步》）&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;在书面前，经历，或年龄，决定了读到什么。&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;em&gt;Books are mirrors. Standing in front of it, I see my past, present, and possibly my futures.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div align = "left"&gt;
   &lt;div&gt;**********&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;以前为了写作文，只要凑够素材，就可以停下。所以，我从来没有翻开过&lt;strong&gt;《自由在高处》&lt;/strong&gt;。今年读完了，相见恨晚，当时很多烦恼都在书里得到了解答。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;以前不爱看正经书，现在为了在对手方面前不失专业，必须读懂一切资料。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;以前只会空口背“吾十有五而志于学，三十而立，四十而不惑，五十而知天命，六十而耳顺，七十而从心所欲，不逾矩”，听了曾仕强讲&lt;strong&gt;《易经》&lt;/strong&gt;，才发现孔子在用亲身经历教导我们，一定要不断学习探索，找到自己的原则，知天命之前都有试错的机会。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;以前不懂什么叫学术，被迫在哥大的图书馆里看过90页材料之后，我知道了什么叫旁征博引，握住了文字里的逻辑线。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;以前听不懂英语的声音，直到发现&lt;strong&gt;《Haroun and the Sea of Stories》&lt;/strong&gt;- ”There was once, in the country of Alifbay, a sad city, the saddest of cities, a city so ruinously sad that it had forgotten its name” 嘶嘶声的悲凉开局，“IF FROM SPEED YOU GET YOUR THRILL, TAKE PRECAUTION - MAKE YOUR WILL”打油诗般的荒诞标语，这是拉丁字母的声音。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Snippets"></category><category term="Snippets"></category></entry></feed>