<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Green World - Snippets</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="feeds/snippets.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2023-09-16T21:00:00+08:00</updated><entry><title>杂碎 (Snippets)</title><link href="snippets-zh.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-09-16T21:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2023-09-16T21:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Iris</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-09-16:snippets-zh.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A tree hole to dump thoughts｜思绪杂碎&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;一年前的杂碎板块（Snippets）是用来记录日常情绪化的瞬间的。
一年后，我不再那么emo了，我想拿这个板块来记录思绪（threads of thoughts）。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the threads of thoughts, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I want to weave a coherent net, &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;to wrap innovation and dream.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在 GPT 被狂欢的时代，&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;我像个顽固的守旧派，&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;相信积累 domain knowledge 不可或缺，&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;主动 judge 信息，&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;而不是被动接受 AIGC。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;《大量废弃社会》&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;所以说真正决定“新闻价值”的，是特定时代、国家及人民看待问题的态度，对此做出筛选的人则是编辑和记者。(pp. 4)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“新闻”一词的字面意义就是“新的见闻”。最新发生的事、不常出现的事、发生变化的事容易写成报道，然而那些即使存在问题，却为社会所默许，变化缓慢，难以进入到大众视线当中的事，却总是难以成文。记者的“基本使命”-监督权力并与之斗争。(pp. 5)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;我认为发达国家的民众对媒体越来越不信任的原因不仅在于贫富差距扩大化与网络舆论极端化，还有对“与自身息息相关的问题”被媒体边缘化而感到的不满。(pp. 6)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“商品陈旧化”理论始终是商业模式的核心 (pp. 10)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;在团队分工合作的情况下，工人会经手不同种类服装的整个制作过程，因此在几年后，工人的技术水平会得到提高，工资也会上涨。但在孟加拉国那样的国家里，制作工序和流程被细分化，即使刚刚进厂的工人也能迅速投入工作。甚至有的人进了工厂，整整一年都在安装服装右侧的纽扣。这样的工作无论干上多久，工人的技术水平也不会提升，工资也不会上涨。至于企业方面，由于成本降低，也做好了商品滞销的心理准备，只要整体能盈利就行。(pp. 17)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;才能变现 (pp. 19)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“消费者的成熟””不囿于个人欲望，与社会及自然环境共生意识的觉醒“ (pp. 23)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“惜物”精神 (pp. 59)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;服装行业解决方案：（1）公开价格。案例：10YC，GUSTIN，Everlane，Factelier，People Tree（2）有效利用技术。案例：KASHIYAMA the Smart Tailor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;食品行业井出女士的观点：（1）每人每天都浪费了一碗米饭（2）错失销售机会（3）“便利店记账法”与“销售有效期”（4）奇特的“三分之一”法则（5）将“减少垃圾产生”放在首位（6）借助消费者的力量改变食品行业。案例：多利安面包店、Gragger、食品银行与食品募捐、“凉/烤豆腐指数”、需求预测指数、荻野餐厅、“3010”运动、“狗狗袋”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;如果公司遵循“销量全靠降价”这一方针，顾客会越来越难以感受到商品的真正价值，服装的生产者们也会受到伤害，这对他们双方都是一种辜负。(pp. 70)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“让生产者与顾客双方都满意”的宗旨；精心生产的服装能够改变人们的日常生活；注重保持游戏心态和愉快的心情 (pp. 72)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;它既涉及劳动问题与整个服务业的症结，更是一种诞生于新型商业活动之中的“人为创造的习俗” (pp. 96)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"三方得利"，近江商人，卖家、买家、社会。并不鼓励一味扩张，而是“恰到好处”，并将有益的事物与他人分享。(pp. 97)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“在琳琅满目的商品中挑选”已经成为了顾客所习以为常的行为 (pp. 97)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;所谓的经典，就是抓住事物本质，在任何时代都不会过时的东西，因此无需进行改变。(pp. 119)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;第一代人：从欧洲引进面包和葡萄酒并尝试制作；第二代人：在日本用欧洲的材料制作出正宗地道的产品；第三代人：用日本的原料，结合日本的气候与水土，制作出符合日本人口味的产品 （pp. 120)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;资源共享型社会 (pp. 153)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;道德时尚 (pp. 156)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;始终在价格、流行度或便利性这些可变换的价值上进行竞争，只会让人疲惫不堪。(pp. 167)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;自然而然地与生产者共情 （pp. 174)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Lean In by Sheryl Sandberg《向前一步》&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Even worse, the messages sent to girls can move beyond encouraging superficial traits and veer into explicitly discouraging leadership. (pp. 21)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The gender stereotypes introduced in childhood are reinforced throughout our lives and become self-fulfilling prophecies. (pp. 23)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Women are not thinking about 'having it all,' they are worried about losing it all - their jobs, their children's health, their families' financial stability.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Framing the issue as work-life balance - as if the two were diametrically opposed - practically ensures work will lose out. (pp. 25)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Fear is the root of so many of the barriers that women face. Fear of not being liked. Fear of making the wrong choice. Fear of drawing negative attention. Fear of overreaching. Fear of being judged. Fear of failure. And the holy trinity of fear: the fear of being a bad mother/wife/daughter. (pp. 26)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;undistort the distortion (pp. 35)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;fake it till you feel it (pp. 36)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opportunities are not well defined but, instead, come from someone jumping in to do something. That something then become his job.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is hard to visualize someone as a leader if she is always waiting to be told what to do. (pp. 37)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is no perfect fit when you're looking for the next big thing to do. You have to take opportunities and make an opportunity fit for you. (pp. 38)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For women, "self-doubt becomes a form of self-defense." We put ourselves done before others. (pp. 44)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Owning one's success is key to achieving more success. (pp. 47)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"gender discount" problem (pp. 48)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The goal of a successful negotiation is to achieve our objectives and continue to have people like us. (pp. 50)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;pronouns matter, justify their requests, relentlessly pleasant (pp. 51)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you want to change things, you can't please everyone. If you do please everyone, you aren't making enough progress. (pp. 55)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a long-term dream and an eighteen month plan (pp. 58)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Employees who concentrate on results and impact are the most valuable. Set more personal goals for learning new skills in the next eighteen months. (pp. 63)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Letting the other side make the first offer is often crucial to achieving favorable terms. (pp. 64)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In business, being risk averse can result in stagnation. Seeking out diverse experience is useful preparation for leadership. (pp. 66)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The most common way people give up their power is by thinking they don't have any. (pp. 68)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The men were focusing on how to manage a business and the women focusing on how to manage a career. (pp. 71)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Excel and you will get a mentor. (pp. 73)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Asking for input is not a sign of weakness but often the first step to finding a path forward. (pp. 76)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All advice is autobiographical. (pp. 80)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As we learn to speak appropriately, we lose something in authenticity. (pp. 82)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;not brutally honest but delicately honest (pp. 83)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Great leadership is "conscious" leadership - Fred Kofman&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When communicating hard truths, less is often more, (pp. 85)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Feedback, like truth, is not absolute. Feedback is an opinion, grounded in observations and experiences, which allows us to know what impression we make on others. (pp. 88)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Being open to hearing the truth means taking responsibility for mistakes. (pp. 89-90)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Motivation comes from working on things we care about. It also comes from working with people we care about. (pp. 94)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;True leadership stems from individuality that is honestly and sometimes imperfectly expressed. Strive for authenticity over perfection. (pp. 97)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But when it comes to integrating career and family, planning too far in advance can close doors rather than open them. (pp. 99)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Women wind up leaving the workforce precisely because of things they did to stay in the workforce. (pp. 100)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anyone lucky enough to have options should keep them open. (pp. 110)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It's not about biology, but about consciousness. (pp. 115)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trying to do it all and expecting that it all can be done exactly right is a recipe for disappointment. (pp. 131)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Be a perfectionist in only the things that mattered. (pp. 131)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Done is better than perfect. (pp. 133)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Setting obtainable goals is key to happiness. Instead of perfection, we should aim for sustainable and fulfilling. Success is making the best choices we can... and accepting them. The secret is there is no secret-just doing the best you can with what you've got. (pp. 148)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Whoever has power takes over the noun-and the norm-while the less powerful get an adjective. (pp. 149)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No one wants her achievements modified. (pp. 149)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leadership is about making others better as a result of your presence and making sure that impact lasts in your absence. Social gains are never handed out. They must be seized. (pp. 167)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Equal opportunity is not equal unless everyone receives the encouragement that makes seizing those opportunities possible. (pp. 170)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To feel comfortable with our choices and to feel validated by those around us. (pp. 178)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Our job is not to make young women grateful. It is to make them ungrateful so they keep going. (pp. 182)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Haroun and the Sea of Stories《哈乐与故事海》&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A blind man's blindness must feel twice as wretched then. - Rashid (pp. 22)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Need's a slippery snake. Need's a funny fish: It makes people untruthful. - Butt (pp. 24)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;No story comes from nowhere; new stories are born from old. - Iff (pp. 74)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You know how people are, new things, always new. The old tales, nobody cares. - Iff (pp. 74)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dark, my sirs, has its fascinations: mystery, strangeness, romance ... - Iff (pp. 91)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Don't you know girls have to fool people everyday of their lives if they want to get anywhere? - Blabbermouth (pp. 95)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You keep a lot of different tales in the air, and juggle them up and down, and if you're good you don't drop any. So maybe juggling is a kind of storytelling, too. - Haroun (pp. 97)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That's the trouble with you sad city types: you think a place has to be miserable and dull as ditchwater before you believe it's real. - Blabbermouth (pp. 103)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And is not the Power of Speech the greatest Power of all? Then surely it must be exercised to the full. - Butt the Hoopoe (pp. 107)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is all for Love, which is a wonderful and dashing matter. But which can also be a very foolish thing. - Mali (pp. 108)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Silence had its own grace and beauty (just as speech could be graceless and ugly); and that Action could be as noble as words; and that creatures of darkness could be as lovely as the children of the light. - Haroun (pp. 113)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So peace with the Chupwalas means Peace with their Shadows, too. - Mudra (pp. 121)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is a sad time when a Chupwala cannot even trust his own shadow. - Mudra (pp. 122)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We lost touch with our beginnings, with our roots, our wellspring, our source. - Iff (pp. 134)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The worst things of all can look so normal and, well, dull. - Haroun (pp. 141)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;War makes people crude. (pp. 174)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They had talked through everything so fully, fought hard, remained united, supported each other when required to do so, and in general looked like a force with a common purpose. All those arguments and debates, all that openness, had created powerful bonds of fellowship between them. / Their vows of silence and their habits of secrecy had made them suspicious and distrustful of one another. (pp. 175)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Happy endings are much rarer in stories, and also in life, than most people think. You could almost say they are the exceptions, not the rule. - Walrus (pp. 191)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Happy endings must come at the end of something. If they happen in the middle of a story, or an adventure, or the like, all they do is cheer things up for a while. - Walrus (pp. 192)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Money isn't everything; no money is nothing at all. - Rashid &amp;amp; Mail Coach (pp. 197)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;What It Takes by Stephen A. Schwarzman《苏世民：我的经验与教训》&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Teaching, I came to believe, is about more than sharing knowledge. You have to remove the obstacles in people's way.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s just as hard to achieve big goals as it is small ones. The only difference is that bigger goals have much more significant consequences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It’s at these inflection points that the most important lessons in business and life are learned.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The best executives are made, not born. They absorb information, study their own experiences, learn from their mistakes, and evolve.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But what I lacked in basic economics, I made up for with my ability to see patterns and develop new solutions and paradigms, and with the sheer will to turn my ideas into reality.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;applying resources to change paradigms in a way that will have an impact on lives, not just the bottom line.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I believe that education is a discipline. The object of this discipline is to learn how to think. Once we have mastered this, we can use it to learn a vocation, appreciate art, or read a book. Education simply enables us to appreciate the ever-changing drama fashioned of God’s own hand, life itself. Education continues when we leave the classroom. Our associations with friends, our participation in clubs all increase our store of knowledge. In fact, we never stop learning until we die. My fellow officers and I just hope that you will become aware of the purpose of education and follow its basic tenets, questioning and thinking, for the rest of your life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At some point in life, we have to figure out who we are, he said. The sooner we do it the better, so we can pursue the opportunities that are right for us, not some false dream created by others.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People often think theirs is the only reality, but there are as many realities as there are individuals. The more you see of them, the more likely you are to make sense of them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;For a business to succeed, each part has to work on its own and with all the other parts.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;As long as you can be honest and rational and are able to explain yourself, there is no reason to feel uncomfortable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ability to deal with uncertainty, self-confidence, intellectual curiosity, courtesy, an ability to adjust to new situations, emotional stability under pressure, a zero-defect mentality, an unwavering commitment to behaving with integrity and striving for excellence in all we choose to do.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Investors are always looking for great investments. The easier you make it for them, the better for everyone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People who succeed in finance must start with repetitive practice before they can ever hope to achieve mastery.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There are people who come to finance from other professions, from law or the media perhaps, but the best I’ve ever worked with grew up in it. They learned by doing the fundamental analysis.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The most important asset in business is information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The more you know, the more perspectives you have and the more connections you can make, which allow you to anticipate issues.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deals ultimately come down to a few key points that matter most to each side. If you can clear everything else away and focus on these points, you will be an effective negotiator.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Listening closely and watching the way people talk puts me much closer to answering the question I’m always asking myself, which is: How can I help? If I can help someone and become a friend to their situation, everything else follows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is nothing more interesting to people than their own problems. If you can find out what they are and come up with solutions, they will want to talk to you no matter their rank or status.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Money is a poor cure for a bad situation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When you disagree, it’s important to get your opinions on record so you aren’t blamed later when things go wrong.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People who are 10s sense problems, design solutions, and take the business in new directions without being told to do so.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sense of working for a single, coherent entity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Success is about taking advantage of those rare moments of opportunity that you can’t predict but come to you provided you’re alert and open to major changes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People in a tough spot will often focus on their own problems when the answer may lie in fixing someone else’s.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To invest only when values have recovered at least 10 percent from their lows.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;While most investors say they are interested in making money, they are actually interested in psychological comfort. They would rather be part of the herd, even when the herd is losing money, than make the hard decisions that yield the greatest rewards.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Finance is an industry that encourages self-delusion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first was focus. The second way to maximize your chances of achieving excellence was to ask for help when needed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In any conversation with someone you don’t know, you should always be patient and keep asking questions until you find a place of common ground.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hearing the nuance in someone’s voice or seeing that person’s body language told me as much as anything he or she said.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We enter these situations with financing, a strategy to transform the business, and expert operating professionals, and we invest the time needed to turn them around.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They feel threatened by bad news and dread the uncertainty of change and the hard work it demands. This tendency makes them passive and rigid at the very moment they should be most active and flexible.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;At its best, worrying is playful, engaging work that requires that you never switch off.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“But there are times when you just have to stand up and write a check. You have to show customers that you own this, because if you don’t, they’re not going to trust you ever again.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Success breeds arrogance and complacency, he said. You only learn from your mistakes and when the worst happens.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“When we buy companies and real estate, it’s like planting crops. You put seeds in the ground, you water, and the seeds start growing, but you can’t see the crop yet. Then they grow very high, and it will be a great crop, and you will be very, very happy.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When people are being stopped, for no good reason, from buying what they need, the system has to adjust.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;buying in the right way at the right time in the cycle&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Three tests for a new line of business: It must have the potential to be hugely rewarding for investors. It must add to Blackstone’s intellectual capital. And it must have a 10 in charge of it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;That experience taught me that the prestige of that first job didn’t matter nearly as much as the opportunities I lost to develop my skills.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I am now quite certain that China is no longer an elective course for future generations; rather, it is core curriculum, and Schwarzman Scholars is the best version of that curriculum we could devise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What America viewed as a request for China to modernize its economy and bring it in line with the standards required by international law, China viewed as a demand to become more like America.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;finding fantastic people and giving them the chance to be the best at what they do&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“bilinguals of the future,” fluent in both AI and their own academic discipline, scientific or not.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;But as science and technology have accelerated, introducing the concept of machines which are designed to replicate human intelligence, there are many new moral, philosophical, and ethical questions to consider regarding what it means to be human and what values we want our technology to reflect.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In a world that is changing so quickly, it’s quite possible this type of cross-institutional, global collaboration is the only way to ensure a safe and prosperous future for us all.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I have long believed that education is the passport to a better life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We all have a duty to not only preserve the knowledge that is handed to us but also develop it in a way that improves its relevance and impact for future generations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regardless of how you begin your careers, it is important to realize that your life will not necessarily move in a straight line.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Nudge by Richard H. Thaler and Cass R. Sunstein《助推》&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Libertarian Paternalism (pp.6)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The false assumption is that almost all people, almost all the time, make choices that are in their best interest or at the very least are better than the choices that would be made by someone else. (pp.13)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first misconception is that it is possible to avoid influencing people’s choices. (pp.14)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The second misconception is that paternalism always involves coercion. (pp.15)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“anchoring and adjustment” – the bias occurs because the adjustments are typically insufficient. (pp.27)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Second marriage is the triumph of hope over experience. (pp.34)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Loss aversion helps produce inertia, meaning a strong desire to stick with your current holdings. (pp.35)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One of the causes of status quo bias is a lack of attention. (pp.37)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The combination of loss aversion and mindless choosing is one reason why if an option is designated as the default, it will usually (but not always!) attract a large market share. (pp.38)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Automatic system (fast and intuitive) vs. Reflective system (slow and reflective) (pp.41)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;One reason why teenagers are such risky drivers is that their Automatic Systems have not had much practice, and using the Reflective System is much slower. (pp.44)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hot-cold empathy gap – underestimate the strength of the effect (pp.52)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Two semiautonomous selves: a farsighted “Planner” and a myopic “Doer” (pp.52)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Econs are pretty unsociable creatures. They communicate with others only if they can gain something from the encounter, they care about their reputations (because a good reputation is valuable), and they will learn from others if actual information can be obtained, but Econs are not followers of fashion. Their hemlines do not go up and down except for practical reasons, they do not wear ties, and if they did they would not grow narrower and wider simply as a matter of style. (pp.64)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first involves the information that seems to be conveyed by other people’s answers; the second involves peer pressure and the desire not to face the disapproval of the group. (pp.68-69)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is an important clue here about how seemingly similar groups, cities, and even nations can converge on very different beliefs and actions simply because of modest and even arbitrary variations in starting points. (pp.70)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collective conservatism (pp.71)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Informational cascade, reputational cascade (pp.74)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Identity-based cognition (pp.79)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pluralistic ignorance (pp.81)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The nudge is emphatically social; it often turns out to be a kind of permission slip. (pp.81)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If people wrongly think that most people are committed to a long-standing social norm, a small nudge correcting that misperception can inaugurate large-scale change. (pp.82)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The golden rule of libertarian paternalism: offer nudges that are most likely to help and least likely to inflict harm. (pp.91)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People are most likely to need nudges when decisions require scarce attention, when decisions are difficult, when people do not get prompt feedback, and when they have trouble translating aspects of the situation into terms that they can easily understand. (pp.91)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To all their virtues, markets often give companies a strong incentive to cater to (and profit from) our frailties, rather than to try to eradicate them or to minimize their effects. (pp.92)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The situation is not structured to provide good feedback. For example, we usually get feedback only on the options we select, not the ones we reject. Unless people go out of their way to experiment, they may never learn about alternatives to the familiar ones. (pp.98)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The benefit of having so little choice is that the chef is authorized to serve you things you would never have thought to order. (pp.98)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Stimulus response compatibility (pp.104)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you want to encourage some actions or activity, Make It Easy. (pp.106)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Channel factors, Kurt Lewin (pp.106)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Postcompletion” error: when you have finished your main task, you tend to forget things relating to previous steps. (pp.114)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“Forcing function”: in order to get what you want, you have to do something else first. (pp.114)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A self-nudge can be called a “snudge.” (pp.121)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Elimination by aspects (pp.122)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Collaborative filtering (pp.124)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Structuring choice sometimes means helping people to learn, so they can later make better choices on their own. (pp.124)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;4 questions about a particular choice architecture: Who chooses? Who uses? Who pays? Who profits? (pp.125)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Curation is essential for any business that wants to compete with online giants. (pp.131)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Good curation combines getting rid of bad options and introducing novel ones. (pp.132)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Work consists of whatever a body is obliged to do. Play consists of whatever a body is not obliged to do. Whenever we can make some activity seem like play, pique our curiosity, or build excitement or anticipation, we will find that people are not only willing to undertake that activity; they even may be willing to pay for the opportunity. (pp.133)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A free-goody can be a better inducement than cash because it offers that rarest of commodities: a guilt-free pleasure. (pp.135)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;So good choice architects not only have to pick a standardized way to measure but also need to think carefully about how to report the findings, so that Humans do not get confused. (pp.139)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;It is time for disclosure rules to make use of at least twentieth-century technology. (pp.142)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Smart disclosure: timely release of complex information and data in standardized, machine readable formats. (pp.142-43)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;First, complex information should be disclosed and made available in a format that is both standardized and machine readable. Second, any organization, public or private, that keeps track of information involving the behavior of individuals or households should generally make that data accessible to them. (pp.143)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Any aspect of choice architecture consisting of friction that makes it harder for people to obtain an outcome that will make them better off (by their own lights). (pp.153)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Dark patterns: an assortment of online practices that are specifically designed to manipulate people (in order to take their money). (pp.153)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Some expenses may increase with freedom. But the costs from overspending are not nearly as high as the gains that freedom provides. With expense freedom, employees will be able to make quick decisions to spend money in ways that help the business. (pp.164)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Every part of the tax system should be designed with a careful eye on the sludge burden. (pp.175)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We make a distinction we find useful in thinking about consumer decision-making in general, namely whether the most important aspect of the consumer experience depends on the process of choosing or using. (pp.220)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Mortgages are more like monitors and credit cards are more like tennis rackets. (pp.220)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When purchasing insurance, choose the largest deductible available. (pp.238)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If a tax is understood to be responding to a serious problem, people might respond even more than they would to the purely economic incentive. (pp.296)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Publicity principle: no choice architect in the public or private sector should adopt a policy that she would not be able or willing to defend publicly. (pp.327)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Thaler has long said that he hopes a day will come when the field of behavioral economics no longer exists because economists will incorporate the existence of Humans in their analyses to whatever extent that is appropriate (or even optimal). (pp.336)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;All policies require some choice architecture, just as all products require some kind of design. (pp.336)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;其他/Others&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I only hope that we never lose sight of one thing - that it was all started by a mouse. - Walt Disney&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Speak less than you know; have more than you show. 怀璧慎显，博识谨言。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When I was young and free and my imagination had no limits, I dreamed of changing the world. As I grew older and wiser, I discovered the world would not change, so I shortened my sights somewhat and decided to change only my country. But it, too, seemed immovable. As I grew into my twilight years, in one last desperate attempt, I settled for changing only my family, those close to me, but alas, they would have none of it. And now, as I lie on my deathbed, I suddenly realize: If I had only changed myself first, then by example, I would have changed my family. From their inspiration and encouragement, I would then have been able to better my country and who knows, I may have even changed the world. - Westminster Abbey&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;我们最后变成什么样，并不取决于我们选择了哪条道路，而是取决于我们的内心。- 欧·亨利&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;莫言见到马尔克斯后要说的第一句话：“先生，我在梦中与你一起喝过咖啡，但哥伦比亚的咖啡里是有中国绿茶的味道。”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;周国平：爱是关切，关切就会在乎，在乎就难免挑剔，于是生出无穷的恩怨。（保护爱心，拒绝冷漠）&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;泰戈尔：把自己活成一道光，因为你不知道谁会借着你的光，走出黑暗。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;给品类取名的要点：有根、好感、直白&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;或许，成年人的孤独，就是悲喜自渡，而这也正是我们难得的自由。-马尔克斯《百年孤独》&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;白日不到处，青春恰自来。苔花如米小，也学牡丹开。-清·袁枚&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;5个谈话技巧：（1）先用认同提醒对方“咱们是一伙的” （2）表达赞赏，调动情感力量（3）帮对方看到事情的另一面（4）重申双方共同的价值观（5）提出具体行动方案，以此建立起共同成长的伙伴关系。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;领导力是你能不能，敢不敢让人、让事情产生积极的改变。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;真正的领导力是做自己。-万维钢《真正的领导力是做自己》&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;斯隆认为：专业人才不应该透露自己的兴趣、信念和私人生活，这是他的私事，和专业无关，所以他都隐去了。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;作为一个社会人，如果你在领导位置上，不管是在企业还是在政府，你得把自己的爱好隐藏起来。因为，你的爱好就是别人进攻你的缺口。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;喜怒哀乐之未发，谓之中；发而皆中节，谓之和。中也者，天下之大本也；和也者，天下之达道也。致中和，天地位焉，万物育焉。-《中庸》&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;什么是素直之心？简单说，就是没有束缚的心，即不被情感、经验、偏见、利害关系等束缚，客观而真实地看待事物的心。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;年轻人，希望你们在追逐梦想的路上，能够抽出一点时间来静思冥想，排除无谓的干扰，保持纯正的内心。希望你们不被五光十色的世界迷惑，不被物欲和金钱左右，能够始终不忘初心，一心一意。-松下幸之助&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;不完美，不是孩子的缺点，而是人的特点。-新教育研究院院长李镇西&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;喜欢的东西还是喜欢，只是不再强求；害怕的东西还是害怕，只是敢于面对。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“八胜七败”维持相对的平衡，是世间万事得以永续的秘诀。-松浦弥太郎&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;人活得累，不是人太聪明，而是人太愚蠢。绝大多数的人为活而活，而不是为生命而活。这是人的悲哀。多数的人，把自己的一生活成一个夺取的过程，而不是认识和体验生命的过程。-傅菲&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;每个人的高度和宽度，就是活着的境界。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;真正的庄重是有温度的，这种温度就是人情味。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;朋友，始终是那些久处不厌的人。-马德&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;人生不受环境的支配，只受自己习惯思想的恐吓。-赫胥黎&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;“狐媚”面前，宜自律，须自持；“贪泉”面前，自强者改造环境，清廉者不惧环境，弱者则被环境所吞噬。-齐世明&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;语言的尽头是音乐的开始。-海涅&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;不要拒绝意外，因为意外是你与世界互相试探的机会。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;图图：非洲人有一种叫作ubuntu的东西，他们相信每个人都是因别人的存在而存在的。“我”与大家紧紧相连。在他们看来，“孤独的人”是不存在的，因为你为群体的共同利益而工作，所以你存在于群体中。当你有了归属，也就有了你自己。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;亚里士多德：羡慕是别人的好运给自己造成的痛苦。在当下，有些人衡量人生价值的标准，不是自己本身的内在价值，而是环境与他人等参照物-别人得到的你没得到，却不去想一想你得到的别人也未必拥有。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;法国社会学家布尔迪厄《继承人》：出身不利的孩子详细学习着帕特农神庙的平面图，却未曾离开自己居住的省份。对一些人来说，学到精英文化是用很大的代价换来的成功；对另一些人来说，这只是一种继承。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;成长是为了让自己的精神世界能够容纳更多相反的道理，并且知道在什么时候使用什么道理。-罗振宇&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;艺术是一种非常人道的方式，能让生命变得比较可以忍受。-库尔特·冯内古特&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;管理的本质是传递善意和激发潜力。-彼得·德鲁克&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;千年不变的中国古老土地上延续的日常生活&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;平凡的原野上，一棵树的姿态，一株草的生长，一只鸟的飞翔，这里边含有永恒的无限的美。-冯至 中国最杰出的抒情诗人&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;威尔伯：“人类是在昆斯伯罗大桥上捉甲虫吗？”夏洛：“不，他们不捉任何东西。他们只是在桥上走过来走过去，老以为另一边有更好的东西。如果他们在这桥顶上倒过头来静静地等着，也许真有好东西会来。可是不，人类每一分钟都在向前冲啊，冲啊，冲啊。我很高兴我是一只生网的蜘蛛。”-《夏洛的网》&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;你做三四月的事，在八九月自有答案。-余世存《时间之书》&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;（1）教育的“边界”将被打破。“订阅式在线教育”（2）“专业”选择将变得越发不重要，程式化的技能会被淘汰。“微学历证书”（3）实习越来越重要，有机会尝试更多份工作。人文学科和批判性思维。-黄征宇&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;自大一点念个“臭”。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;一个人若想较好地把握人生，不妨保持“三心二意”：知足心、上进心、童心和诚意、善意。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;自由比权利重要，知识比金钱永恒，平凡比盛名可贵，执着比聪明难得。-张弥曼&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;其一，现代国家在以经济发展为核心的目标导向下，人力变成了一种资源，而生命在本质上就是一种时间进程，因而对每个人的生命时间进行统一管理，便成为重要的经济发展要素。其二，如何对有限的物质资源进行适当分配是国家管理要务，而时间就成为一个有效的筛选标准。比如“教育时间”。教育的理念本应让学生学会做事情，但今天的教育进度不是按照学习成效，而是按照时间来推进的。然后再用时间当门槛，把在有限的时间内学不会的人淘汰掉。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;动词哲学&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;原本山川，极命草木&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;极命草木：极尽所能地珍惜爱护一草一木、一鸟一虫，乃至所有的生命&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;有一日未死之身，则有一日未闻之道。-顾炎武&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;绝望和希望之间的最佳桥梁，是一个良好的睡眠。-马修·沃克&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;别人的评论，都是建立在他们自己的价值取向上的，实在不足为据。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;心随境转是凡人，境随心转是圣贤。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;我和谁都不争，和谁争我都不屑。-兰德&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;没有疑悔。所以真正的供养布施不在钱物多少，而在能否坦然，生起欢喜，不会后悔。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;敏于事而慎于言。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;我们在荒芜，我们在腐烂。格伦瓦尔德说我们在一个平坦、光滑的世界里腐烂。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;太上，不知有之。吾为太上，不显于外，不示于内，不修于容，不达乎己。为无为，无为而为。-老子&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;四毋：毋固、毋我、毋意、毋必。-《论语》&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;只有虚空才能容纳物体。-《徒然草》&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;21世纪初是个科技迅猛发展的时代，但观察力、判断力、耐力，这些让森林古猿进化成人的能力，不管出于何种原因，已一点点离我们而去。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;神话之所以经久不衰，是因为它们精确捕捉到人的永恒处境。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;人生是由一个总的“悲剧”和无数个“小确幸”组成的。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;当你让自己的生活变得简单，宇宙的法则也会变得简单。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;人生路上的坡道，爬起来挥汗如雨，需要不停地喘气。然而，再怎么艰难、再怎么无奈，这条坡道也一定要爬上去。在这个过程中，我们会积蓄起人生收获的力量。这看似在消耗能量，实际上，却可以积蓄起伟大的力量。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;阴阳大制有六度：天为绳，地为准，春为规，夏为衡，秋为矩，冬为权。-《淮南子·时则训》&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;彼节者有间，而刀刃者无厚，以无厚入有间，恢恢乎其于游刃必有余地矣。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;松弛感=看得透+有办法+能喜欢&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;在成功学的激励下，每个人都想去闯一闯独木桥，在这样的对比中，关爱家人、工作上心、信守诺言、靠谱善良的优质普通人反而显得特别可靠。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;实际上，不管最终的目的多么高大上，大家最开始的出发点都只不过是为了生活得好点。于是，优质普通人的长处便显现出来，他们不是庸碌，而是温和的优秀；他们从不咄咄逼人，总是带着暖暖的厚道。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;你可以这么想，人总有不顺利或疲倦的时候，在那种时候，就把它当成神赐给我们的很长很长的假期。-《悠长假期》&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;书是可能性，是逃跑路线。当你没有选择时，它们给你机会。对流离失所的头脑来说，每一本书都是一座家园。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</content><category term="Snippets"></category><category term="Snippets"></category></entry><entry><title>读后感两篇</title><link href="what-it-takes-and-nudge-zh.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-09-12T21:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2023-09-12T21:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Iris</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-09-12:what-it-takes-and-nudge-zh.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;《苏世民：我的经验与教训》和《助推》读后感。&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;《苏世民：我的经验与教训》&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s at these inflection points that the most important lessons in business and life are learned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What It Takes《苏世民：我的经验与教训》在我的人生转折点上给了我很多启示，比如&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of how you begin your careers, it is important to realize that your life will not necessarily move in a straight line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;抛开代笔的影响，这本书的口吻和观念带着美国式的激进，但不失谦逊。苏世民本人非常看重教育，他相信“education is the passport to a better life”（教育是通向更好生活的通行证），并且认为教育的意义在于让人有质疑和思考的能力：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe that education is a discipline. The object of this discipline is to learn how to think. Once we have mastered this, we can use it to learn a vocation, appreciate art, or read a book. Education simply enables us to appreciate the ever-changing drama fashioned of God’s own hand, life itself. Education continues when we leave the classroom. Our associations with friends, our participation in clubs all increase our store of knowledge. In fact, we never stop learning until we die. My fellow officers and I just hope that you will become aware of the purpose of education and follow its basic tenets, questioning and thinking, for the rest of your life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;从宾州的布料商店，到短跑选手，到推翻耶鲁校规，到主动拜访大佬Averell Harriman，到出海，到从军，到质疑哈佛MBA太水，到卖掉雷曼，到创立黑石。他有野心，有眼力，也有底线。底线就是不管市场好坏，永远用对的方法做对的事，不要让投资人亏钱。就算亏钱了，也要自掏腰包，负责：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there are times when you just have to stand up and write a check. You have to show customers that you own this, because if you don’t, they’re not going to trust you ever again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;他真的很真诚。愿意倾听，解决别人的问题（其实就是解决自己的问题）&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any conversation with someone you don’t know, you should always be patient and keep asking questions until you find a place of common ground.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is nothing more interesting to people than their own problems. If you can find out what they are and come up with solutions, they will want to talk to you no matter their rank or status.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;因为本科学的是行为学，他常常会探究人的心理，这点人情味让他在金融业和政界如鱼得水。知心而明鉴，明鉴而智行。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hearing the nuance in someone’s voice or seeing that person’s body language told me as much as anything he or she said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While most investors say they are interested in making money, they are actually interested in psychological comfort. They would rather be part of the herd, even when the herd is losing money, than make the hard decisions that yield the greatest rewards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finance is an industry that encourages self-delusion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;真的好想去苏世民书院进修啊～&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;《助推》&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thaler has long said that he hopes a day will come when the field of behavioral economics no longer exists because economists will incorporate the existence of Humans in their analyses to whatever extent that is appropriate (or even optimal) . (pp.336)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nudge《助推》是一本有关行为经济学的书，用风趣、实用的方式谈学术。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;在传统经济学中，总是假设人是理性的，行为受动机驱使：&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Econs are pretty unsociable creatures. They communicate with others only if they can gain something from the encounter, they care about their reputations (because a good reputation is valuable), and they will learn from others if actual information can be obtained, but Econs are not followers of fashion. Their hemlines do not go up and down except for practical reasons, they do not wear ties, and if they did they would not grow narrower and wider simply as a matter of style. (pp.64)
（我很像以上段落中的Econ）&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;但是现实中，人（Humans）会有很多心理或者行为上的偏差/失误，让许多经济学理论失效。因为人是人，所以他们需要外力去助推他们实现理性行为，比如投资养老金、节能减排、不乱刷信用卡、坚持锻炼等等。作者把这种助推的理念称之为自由主义的父权主义（Libertarian Paternalism），只有Econs才能想出来的词。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The golden rule of libertarian paternalism: offer nudges that are most likely to help and least likely to inflict harm. (pp.91)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People are most likely to need nudges when decisions require scarce attention, when decisions are difficult, when people do not get prompt feedback, and when they have trouble translating aspects of the situation into terms that they can easily understand. (pp.91)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;助推的关键在于设计选择结构（Choice Architecture），最好的方法就是让对的选择变简单（Make It Easy）！比如，自助餐把沙拉放在最前面，引导人们健康饮食；让人在申请驾照的时候决定是否捐献器官；把投资养老金设置为默认选项等等。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;书中的观点给政策设计提供了很多启示，简而言之就是让政策人性化，既考虑到人性的弱点，也在执行时助推人的行为，让一切变简单，而不是制造很多sludge来阻碍执行。&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;同时，书里的行为偏差（mental accounting, loss aversion, etc）也对个人的消费行为进行了剖析。基于这些研究，我建成了自己的理财模型-貔貅，助推自己早日买上金条。&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Snippets"></category><category term="Snippets"></category></entry><entry><title>写在读书日</title><link href="on-world-book-day-zh.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2023-04-23T21:00:00+08:00</published><updated>2023-04-23T21:00:00+08:00</updated><author><name>Iris</name></author><id>tag:None,2023-04-23:on-world-book-day-zh.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;书是生活的影子，是一面镜子。&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;h3&gt;书是生活的影子，是一面镜子。&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;书总在意想不到的时候出现.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;em&gt;Books are shadows of life, casting shadows in my heart.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div align = "left"&gt;
   &lt;div&gt;**********&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;还在城大的一个雨夜，为了听龙应台的讲座，买了一本&lt;strong&gt;《天长地久》&lt;/strong&gt;，从此，和家人在一起就是我最期待的天长地久。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;曾经带着&lt;strong&gt;《What it takes》&lt;/strong&gt;（《苏世民：我的经验与教训》）去建行面试，读完第二章，我知道自己缺了什么。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;在最迷茫的时候，遇到了南怀瑾老师的&lt;strong&gt;《禅与生命的认知初讲》&lt;/strong&gt;，痛苦的时候，就念老师说的“去你妈的”，滚吧！&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;几个月前看完了拖了几年的&lt;strong&gt;《灰犀牛》&lt;/strong&gt;，前几天突然在爸爸的书架上找到了&lt;strong&gt;《黑天鹅》&lt;/strong&gt;，书页已经泛黄，老爸看没看完我不知道，但是我今年一定会看。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;最近“现代化”是人民日报上的高频词，前两天爸爸带回来一本&lt;strong&gt;《中国式现代化论纲》&lt;/strong&gt;，我多少要研读一下。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;给弟弟买生日礼物，为了凑包邮，我选择了&lt;strong&gt;《Lean In》&lt;/strong&gt;（《向前一步》）&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;在书面前，经历，或年龄，决定了读到什么。&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;em&gt;Books are mirrors. Standing in front of it, I see my past, present, and possibly my futures.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div align = "left"&gt;
   &lt;div&gt;**********&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;以前为了写作文，只要凑够素材，就可以停下。所以，我从来没有翻开过&lt;strong&gt;《自由在高处》&lt;/strong&gt;。今年读完了，相见恨晚，当时很多烦恼都在书里得到了解答。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;以前不爱看正经书，现在为了在对手方面前不失专业，必须读懂一切资料。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;以前只会空口背“吾十有五而志于学，三十而立，四十而不惑，五十而知天命，六十而耳顺，七十而从心所欲，不逾矩”，听了曾仕强讲&lt;strong&gt;《易经》&lt;/strong&gt;，才发现孔子在用亲身经历教导我们，一定要不断学习探索，找到自己的原则，知天命之前都有试错的机会。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;以前不懂什么叫学术，被迫在哥大的图书馆里看过90页材料之后，我知道了什么叫旁征博引，握住了文字里的逻辑线。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;以前听不懂英语的声音，直到发现&lt;strong&gt;《Haroun and the Sea of Stories》&lt;/strong&gt;- ”There was once, in the country of Alifbay, a sad city, the saddest of cities, a city so ruinously sad that it had forgotten its name” 嘶嘶声的悲凉开局，“IF FROM SPEED YOU GET YOUR THRILL, TAKE PRECAUTION - MAKE YOUR WILL”打油诗般的荒诞标语，这是拉丁字母的声音。&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Snippets"></category><category term="Snippets"></category></entry></feed>